Daniel C. Opolot

Email: daniel.opolot@uct.ac.za

Mobile: +27-790949893

Website: epoletdeniel sithub ic/

Website: opolotdaniel.github.io/

Summary

I am a postdoctoral research fellow at the African Institute of Financial Markets and Risk Management (AIFMRM), University of Cape Town. I have been based at AIFMRM since September 2016.

I completed my PhD in Economics in June 2015 at the School of Business and Economics (UNU-MERIT), Maastricht University. Before that, I studied a BSc. in Mathematics and Physical, and an MSc. in Astronomy.

My primary research interests are in:

- Game theory applied to understanding strategic behaviour of firms, consumers and politicians in competitive settings, and the respective policy implications for achieving optimal behaviour.
- Social network analysis here, I study the structures of online social networks (e.g. Facebook, twitter, etc.) and how they can be optimally used as a medium of information exchange (e.g. fake news and opinions), and the diffusion of products and behaviour. I also study other forms of social and economic networks (e.g. Research and Development networks, collaboration networks in academia, citation networks, etc.). I examine how collaboration and information sharing in such networks impacts production costs and productivity.

Positions held

• AIFMRM, University of Cape Town Post Doctoral Research Fellow	Cape Town, SA Sep. 2016 –
$ \overset{\textbf{Maastricht University (School of Business and Economics} - \textbf{SBE)}}{\textit{Lecturer}} $	Maastricht, NL Aug. 2014 – July 2016
EDUCATION	
• UNU-MERIT/SBE, Maastricht University PhD in Economics - Thesis Title: The evolution of beliefs and strategic behaviour	Maastricht, NL Sept. 2010 – June 2015
• UNU-MERIT, Maastricht University Postgraduate Coursework on Innovation and Technical Change	Maastricht, NL Sept. 2009 – July 2010
• University of Cape Town Hon. & MSc. Astronomy	Cape Town, SA Jan. 2007 – July 2009
Mbarara University of Science and Technology BSc. (Mathematics and Physics) with Education	Mbarara, Uganda Sept. 2003 – July 2006

FIELDS

Microeconomics - Theory

Game theory and models of social learning

Microeconomics - Empirical

Social network analysis and economics of science

RESEARCH

• Papers under Revise and Resubmit

- On the relationship between p-dominance and stochastic stability in networks. International Journal of Game Theory [Theory paper]
- Papers under Review in journals
 - o Strategic diffusion in networks through contagion (joint with Théophile T. Azomahoua) [Theory paper]

- How central agents affect group behaviour and the speed of learning [Theory paper]
- Prejudice, group cohesion and the dynamics of disagreement [Theory paper]
- o Discussants (joint with Co-Pierre Georg and Michael E. Rose) [Empirical paper]

• Working Papers

- o Costly word-of-mouth learning in networks (joint with Théophile T. Azomahoua) [Theory paper]
- o Informal intellectual collaboration with central colleagues (joint with Co-Pierre Georg and Michael E. Rose) [Empirical paper]

Work in Progress

- o The Persistence of corruption (joint with Davina Osei) [Empirical/Theory paper]
- o The rate of scientific progress and the structure of the scientific communities (joint with Michael E. Rose) [Theory/Empirical paper]
- Local interactions and long-run stability in evolutionary models [Theory paper]
- Information percolation in exit games [Theory paper]

Teaching Experience

AIFMRM, University of Cape Town

Cape Town, SA

Tutor

2018

o Market Risk: Market instruments and measurement of their associated risk (Master course)

School of Business and Economics, Maastricht University

Maastricht, NL

2014 - 2016

Instructor

o Globalization debate: How globalization has shaped international trade and economic growth

• Macroeconomics: First year undergraduate course

School of Business and Economics, Maastricht University

Maastricht, NL

2014 - 2016

2006

Teaching Assistant

• Microeconomics: First and second year courses

o International Economics & European Markets: Second year course

Eden International School

Mbarara, Uganda

High School Teacher

o Mathematics and Physics: Ordinary and Advanced Levels

Professional Activities

• Conference Presentations

- The Africa Meeting of the Econometric Society: Rabat, Morocco, upcoming, 11-13 July 2019
- o 5th European Meeting on Game Theory (SING15): Turku, Finland, upcoming, 2-4 July 2019
- o Royal Economic Society Conference: University of Warwick, April 2019
- o Asian Meeting of the Econometric Society: Sogang University, Seoul, Korea, June. 2018 (Paper accepted but I could not participate in the conference)
- o Royal Economic Society Conference: University of Sussex, U.K., March 2016
- o Royal Economic Society Postgraduate Presentation Meetings and Job Market: Westminster Business School, 2016
- o World Congress of the Econometric Society: Montréal Canada, Aug. 2015
- UNU-MERIT and MGSoG conference: Maastricht NL, Nov. 2014
- o China Meeting of the Econometric Society: Xiamen, China, June 2014
- o Royal Economic Society Postgraduate Presentation Meetings and Job Market: London U.K., January 2014
- The 25th International Conference on Game Theory: Stony Brook University, New York, July 2014
- o 10th Workshop on Networks in Economics and Sociology: Utrecht School of Economics, Nov. 2011

Seminar Presentations

- o School of Economics: University of Cape Town, 05 Nov. 2018
- Centre for Competition Law and Economics: Stellenbosch University, 25 Oct. 2018
- o AIFMRM Seminars: University of Cape Town, SA, May & Oct. 2018

- o The Research Unit in Behavioural Economics and Neuroeconomics: University of Cape Town, July 2017
- o Department of Economics: Stellenbosch University, 07 Aug. 2017
- o School of Economics: University of Cape Town, June 2017
- o Department of Economics Seminars: University of Pretoria, April 2017
- o Aix-Marseille School of Economics GREQAMs: Marseille, Feb. 2016
- o Centre d'Economie de La Sorbonne and Paris School of Economics: University of Paris 1, Mar. 2013
- o Université de Cergy Pontoise THEMA séminaires: Cergy-Pontoise, Feb. 2013
- o Cournot séminaires at Bureau d'Economie Théorique et Appliquée (BETA) Strasbourg: Strasbourg, Jan. 2013
- o Maastricht Lecture Series in Economics: Maastricht, Nov. 2012

• Refeering Activities

• Journal of Economic Behaviour & Organization, International Journal of Game Theory

• Member of:

• Southern African Market Research Association (professional body), American Economic Association, Econometric Society, Royal Economic Society

AWARDS

• Funding awards

- o URC Postdoctoral Fellowship: University of Cape Town, Jan. 2017 Dec. 2018
- o Econometric Society World Congress travel grant: Aug. 2015
- o UNU Ph.D fellowship: Maastricht University, Sept. 2009 July 2014
- o The South African Square Kilometre Array (SKA) fellowship: University of Cape Town, Jan. 2008 Aug. 2009
- The National Astrophysics and Space Science Programme (NASSP) fellowship: University of Cape Town, Jan. 2007
 Dec. 2008
- o Government Merit Scholarship: Mabrara University, Aug. 2003 June 2006

Programming Skills

• Languages: Python, Matlab, Mathematica, R

References

• PhD Advisor: Prof. Theophile Azomahou

University of Clermont Auvergne (CERDI), CNRS

Email: theophile.azomahou@uca.fr

T: +33 473 177 515

• Postdoc PI: Prof. Co-Pierre Georg

AIFMRM, University of Cape Town

University of Cape Town

Private Bag X3, Rondebosch 7701, South Africa.

Email: co-pierre.georg@uct.ac.za

• PhD Instructor & Dean of Students: Prof. Robin Cowan

UNU-MERIT, Maastricht University

Boschstraat 24, 6211 AX Maastricht

Email: cowan@merit.unu.edu

• PhD Dissertation Examiner: Prof. Alan Kirman

Center for Social Analysis and Mathematics

54, boulevard, Raspail 75006, Paris France

Email: alan.kirman@univ-amu.fr

Tel.: 01 49 54 83 14

• PhD Dissertation Examiner: Ass. Prof. Arkadi Predtetchinski

School of Business and Economics, Maastricht University

Email: a.predtetchinski@maastrichtuniversity.nl